{"tossups": [{"question": "Plutarch states that this man once remarked that his countrymen did not honor him, but treated him like a tree, rushing to him in a storm, and cutting off his branches in good weather. In battle, this leader sent his slave Sicinnus to deliver a message by row boat that there was infighting in order to lure one side into a battle. This man's exile was due to allegations of bribery and conspiring with (*) Pausanias. According to Thucydides, this man led the building of the Long Walls to protect the Piraeus. After this man's exile, he served in the court of Artaxerxes I as governor of Magnesia. This man got Aristides ostracized in a campaign when he called for the fleet of Athens to expand to 200 triremes. For 10 points, name this Athenian statesman and admiral who won the Battle of Salamis.", "answer": "Themistocles", "subcategory": "Ancient History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "At the beginning of this novel, an Imperial Entomologist believes he has discovered a new species of moth but is told that he only found an abnormal existing species. A Rhodes scholar in this novel tries to explain Anglophile history using a metaphor of a house; that character is named Chacko. One character in this novel is molested at a premiere of The Sound of Music by a vendor named the (*) Orangedrink Lemondrink Man. A Communist who works for Paradise Pickles and Preserves is accused of murdering Sophie Mol by Baby Kochamma in this novel. This novel ends with Rahel and Estha having an incestuous affair. For 10 points, name this novel by Arundhati Roy.", "answer": "The God of Small Things", "subcategory": "Long Fiction", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "One form of this technique uses a parameter equal to n times K-sub-a times M known as the c-value. That technique is used to monitor biomolecular binding events. Another form of this technique examines peaks to find the glass transition temperature. One form of this technique consists of two cells in an adiabatic jacket and is its (*) \"isothermal titration\" variety. One type of this technique used for combustion reactions operates under constant volume to eliminate PV work. One form of this technique measures the change in temperature of a water bath and uses the equation q equals mc delta T. That technique is often performed in coffee cups. For 10 points, name this technique that measures the heat change of a reaction.", "answer": "calorimetry [or calorimeter; accept isothermal titration calorimetry or differential scanning calorimetry or bomb calorimetry or coffee cup calorimetry; prompt on ITC or DSC]", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "George Kelly used his personal construct theory of this concept to develop the repertory grid. Hans Eysenck developed a dubious conception of three axes of this concept, while Raymond Cattell used factor analysis to identify sixteen components of this concept. Gordon Allport contrasted central and cardinal aspects of this concept, which is also described in the HEXACO model. It's not a mental disorder, but looking at (*) ambiguous inkblots can be used to measure this concept. Openness and conscientiousness are two of the big five traits proposed to measure this concept, which is also supposed to be measured by the Myers-Briggs test. For 10 points, identify this concept that characterizes a person that may be introverted or extroverted.", "answer": "personality [prompt on personality trait]", "subcategory": "Social Science", "category": "Social Science"}, {"question": "One politician from this country resigned as Minister of Family Affairs after her doctorate was revoked for plagiarism, before running for mayor. This country's satirical party was the first to gain a seat in the European Parliament. A politician from this country was caught laughing during a speech about lives lost to flooding in this country. A (*) \"Jamaica coalition\" might be formed between the Free Democratic Party and three other parties in this country's next election. The Union parties in this country voted for Armin Laschet to lead their 2021 election campaign. A Green Party led by Robert Habeck and Annalena Baerbock is polling 2nd in this country. For 10 points, name this country whose parliament is the Bundestag.", "answer": "Federal Republic of Germany [accept Bundesrepublik Deutschland]", "subcategory": "Current Events", "category": "Current Events"}, {"question": "Barry McCaffrey was criticized for attacking a line of retreating tanks in a battle two days after the end of this war. April Glaspie was accused of giving tacit approval of the events that led up to this war. In the lead-up to this war, Hill and Knowlton helped manufacture mostly false testimony about babies being ripped out of incubators. After this war, Operation Southern Watch was established to enforce (*) no-fly zones over its losing side's minority populations. Retreating forces in this war were attacked in the \"Highway of Death.\" Norman Schwarzkopf led Operation Desert Shield and Operation Desert Storm during this war, which was entered into by George H.W. Bush. For 10 points, name this conflict which was fought after Iraq invaded Kuwait.", "answer": "The Persian Gulf War [accept Kuwait War before Kuwait is read; accept First Gulf War; accept Second Gulf War; prompt on First Iraq War; do not accept or prompt on \"Iraq War\"]", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One play by this author ends with the lines \"Ladies and gentlemen, in you we trust: There must be happy endings, must, must, must!\" In one work by this writer, a character reveals her true identity to a tribunal of gods to highlight the issues with trying to live virtuously. This playwright wrote a play in which Shui Ta is an alter ego Shen Teh uses to kick out freeloaders in her tobacco shop. In another play by this author who coined the term (*) \"distancing effect,\" Kattrin is killed after Eilif and Swiss Cheese go to work for the military. This playwright wrote the Good Person of Szechwan and Mother Courage and Her Children.  For 10 points, name this German playwright who, alongside Kurt Weill, wrote The Threepenny Opera.", "answer": "Bertolt Brecht", "subcategory": "Drama", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "It's not related to ideal gases, but one model of these materials is derived from kinetic theory and assumes the microscopic behavior of some particles can be treated classically like a pinball machine. That theory was modified using quantum theory by Arnold Sommerfeld. These materials are modeled by the Drude model. These materials have a very small or no band gap. The electric field inside these materials must be (*) zero. A perpendicular magnetic field can be used to find the sign of charge carriers inside these materials in the Hall effect. These materials have a delocalized \"sea\" of electrons. Pure silver is the best one of these materials, since it has the lowest resistivity. For 10 points, name these materials that are contrasted with insulators.", "answer": "conductor [prompt on metal]", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "One film from this country is divided into sections including \"Circle of Manias\" and \"Circle of Blood.\" The director of that film was assassinated after adapting a work by the French Marquis de Sade (\"mar-KEE duh SOD\"), 120 Days of Sodom. This country's genre of murder-mystery thriller is named after its word for yellow. A director from this country included the song (*) \"The Ecstasy of Gold\" in The Good, the Bad and the Ugly. This country's Neorealist movement influenced movies such as Bicycle Thieves, directed by Vittorio De Sica. For 10 points, name this home country of directors Pier Paolo Pasolini and Sergio Leone and the setting of the film Rome, Open City.", "answer": "Italy [yellow in Italian is giallo]", "subcategory": "Other Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A custardy cake from this region called a far is often made with plums or raisins. A bicycle race to this region and back gave its name to a ring-shaped pastry filled with praline creme. The flag of this region contains black and white stripes with nine ermine-spots in the canton. A buttery cake from this region is called the kouign-amann. This region is in the western part of the historic region of Armorica. The mythological region of (*) Ys was located off the coast of this region. This region includes the department of Finist\u00e8re, whose capital is Quimper. Saint-Malo is a popular tourist center in this region, which also includes the city of Brest. Rennes is the capital of this region, which has also historically included the city of Nantes. For 10 points, name this historically Celtic peninsula of northwest France.", "answer": "Brittany [accept Bretagne; accept Breizh; accept Berta\u00e8yn; prompt on France or Celtic France or any description of a northern, Atlantic, western, or northwestern part of France]", "subcategory": "Geography", "category": "Geography"}, {"question": "These people led protests concerning the arrest of Jack Weinberg, which caused Edward Strong to resign. At Sproul Plaza, one of these people, Mario Savio, delivered a speech that urged listeners to \"put your bodies upon the gears\" as part of a Free Speech Movement led by these people. The \"Days of Rage\" were led by an organization of these people, one of whom, Tom Hayden, gave the (*) Port Huron Statement. The Weather Underground began as an organization of these people \"for a Democratic Society.\" These people name a \"Nonviolent Coordinating Committee\" that staged many sit-ins in the South. Four of these people were killed during the Kent State Massacre. For 10 points, name these people who attend universities.", "answer": "college students [accept university students; accept undergraduate or graduate students; accept UC Berkeley students or Cal students; prompt on Californians before \"Days of Rage\"; prompt on anti-Vietnam protesters with \"what kind of people protesting the Vietnam War?\"]", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "In one poem, this author notes that \"The groaning earth in travail and pain... does not restore,\" concluding that \"the dead nations never rise again.\" Another poem by this author claims that a \"soul more white / never through martyrdom of fire was led\" and describes \"the cross I wear upon my breast.\" In a poem by this author, one character defeats serpents called Kenabeek on his way to kill the magician (*) Pearl-Feather. That poem by this author of \"The Jewish Cemetery of Newport\" and \"The Cross of Snow\" is named for a character who was born \"By The Shores of Gitche Gumee\" and falls in love with Minnehaha. For 10 points, name this American poet of The Song of Hiawatha, who also wrote \"Paul Revere's Ride.\"", "answer": "Henry Wadsworth Longfellow", "subcategory": "Poetry", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "These organisms produce a secondary bicyclic amine alkaloid known as Very Fast Death Factor. These organisms undergo nitrogen fixation in anaerobic heterocysts. Spirulina, a biomass of these organisms, contains the pigment phycocyanin. Fossilized biofilms of these organisms are called stromatolites. Banded iron layers were created in the Great (*) Oxygenation event, which was caused by the evolution of these organisms. Lynn Margulis noticed that these organisms have thylakoid membranes and proposed that they are the ancestors of modern plastids in the endosymbiosis hypothesis. For 10 points, name this phylum of prokaryotes often erroneously known as blue-green algae.", "answer": "cyanobacteria [or Cyanophyta; accept blue-green algae until mentioned; prompt on bacteria or prokaryotes; prompt on photoautotrophs; do not accept or prompt on \"algae\"]", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "One of these works uses a D drone note imitating a bagpipe. Another of these pieces begins with the theme (read slowly) A, A, C, B, A, before a high E and a repetition of the same phrase in E major. Flutes and horns are imitated by the upper two and lower two (*) strings in the ninth of these works. A continuous tremolo in the sixth of these works led to its nickname, \"The Trill,\" while the thirteenth of these pieces is nicknamed \"The Devil's Laughter.\" The last of these works features heavy left hand pizzicato and inspired a Rhapsody quoting the Dies Irae by Sergei Rachmaninoff. For 10 points, name this set of twenty-four short violin works composed by an Italian virtuoso.", "answer": "Niccol\u00f2 Paganini's 24 Caprices for Solo Violin [accept 24 Caprices for Solo Violin before \"twenty-four\"]", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Walter Benjamin opens an essay on this concept by comparing this concept's materialism to a Mechanical Turk. Alexander Koj\u00e8ve popularized one idea of this concept caused by the rise of capitalism. A kind of positivism developed by Leopold von Ranke argues that people should not make value judgements about this concept. A book by Francis (*) Fukuyama characterizes the triumph of liberal democracy as the \"end\" of this concept, in a book also titled for \"the last man.\" Thomas Carlyle's \"great man\" theory of this concept is opposed by academics who claim that people drive this concept forward. For 10 points, name this field of study pioneered by Herodotus that focuses on humanity's past.", "answer": "history [accept the end of history]", "subcategory": "Philosophy", "category": "Philosophy"}, {"question": "One ruler from this family forged the Privilegium Maius to elevate their status. That event was in response to Charles IV excluding this family from the Golden Bull of 1356. After losing at the Battle of Leitzersdorf, one member of this family eventually returned the Holy Crown to Mathias Corvinus. Members of this family often used the acronym (*) A.E.I.O.U., including Frederick III. One emperor from this family defeated a French coalition at the Battle of Pavia. The phrase \"The empire on which the sun never sets\" was first applied to an emperor from this family, Charles V. For 10 points, name this Austrian family that controlled the Holy Roman Empire.", "answer": "House of Hapsburg [or House of Habsburg]", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This author described one character as disappointed at not being first in sketching draperies. In that short story by this author, the gardener Bassett and Oscar Cresswell become partners with the protagonist. One character in a short story by this author claims that the house whispers \"There must be more money.\" In that short story, a character exclaims \"Malabar\" before dying, leaving Hester 80,000 pounds. In one short story by this author, (*) Paul rides the title toy for long spans of time in order to predict the winners of races. This author wrote \"The Odour of Chrysanthemums\" and \"The Rocking-Horse Winner,\" in addition to a novel about Constance's relationship with the gamekeeper Oliver Mellors. For 10 points, name this British author of Lady Chatterley's Lover.", "answer": "D.H. Lawrence [accept David Herbert Lawrence]", "subcategory": "Short Fiction", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "These numbers are the solution to equations solved by a cyclic algorithm known as the Chakravala method. a, b, and c are these numbers in the abc conjecture. When these numbers are solutions to the equation x-squared minus n times y-squared equals 1, they can be used to approximate square roots; that is Pell's equation. These numbers are the solution to (*) Diophantine equations. For n greater than 2, no three of these numbers are the solution to x-to-the-n plus y-to-the-n plus z-to-the-n, according to Fermat's Last theorem. Irrational numbers cannot be expressed as the ratio of two of these numbers. For 10 points, name these numbers that have no fractional part.", "answer": "integers [accept positive integers or natural numbers or whole numbers or counting numbers or relatively prime integers or coprime integers before \"Diophantine,\" and prompt afterward; prompt on Z or N; prompt on relatively prime numbers]", "subcategory": "Math", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "A painting by this artist depicts one of the title figures pointing an arrow at a man on his deathbed while the other, clad in green, deposits coins into a chest. In another of this artist's paintings, a nun plays a lute while a man attempts to cut meat from a roasted bird. Another work by this artist is thought to depict the creation of the Earth within a crystal sphere when (*) closed. On the left side of that painting, God presents Eve to Adam while, on the right, sinners are punished by monsters in hell. In the center panel, nude figures are depicted indulging in pleasure around a blue, spherical fountain. For 10 points, name this Dutch artist of Ship of Fools and The Garden of Earthly Delights.", "answer": "Hieronymous Bosch [The unnamed artwork is Death and the Miser]", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A character in this text attempts to send his semen by an eagle, but it is swallowed by a fish instead, leading to the birth of a woman who orders her son to commit niyoga. In this work, one character begs to let in a dog who is a god in disguise after five relatives died climbing a mountain path because of their sins. After one character in this work tells his mother to look at what he has brought, she makes five men all marry the (*) same woman, who was won by shooting a golden fish through its reflection. In this text, the Vishnu Sahasranama is recited to Yudhistira by Bhishma, who is immobilized on a bed of arrows. In this text, Arjuna fights for the Pandavas against the Kauravas. For 10 points, name this epic poem about the Kurusketra war, which contains the Bhagavad Gita.", "answer": "Mahabharata", "subcategory": "Mythology", "category": "Mythology"}], "bonuses": []}